A useful feature within Word is
the ability to merge the contents
of a letter with a database of
clients' names and addresses.
In this example, I'm going to use the
files that you can download from the
vision2learn website to show how you
can link the names and addresses of four
clients to the letter, which can then be
sent out without having to type out each
individual person's names and addresses.
So the first thing I need to do is open
the letter which I have done on the
screen there and to access the mail merge
tool, I need to go to the mailings tab.
So if I click on the mailings tab, this
brings up a range of options and the tool
we're going to use here is the mail merge.
So if I click on the start mail merge,
select a step-by-step mail merge
wizard, that will then bring up the
dialog box on the right-hand side.
Now there are six steps in the
mail merge process and we'll work
through each one individually.
So the first one is select document types.
So what type of document
are you working on?
Well, we're working on a letter, so
we're happy with that and go to step
two and select the starting document.
So how do you want to set up your letters?
And again, we're going to use the first
option here is use the current document.
You could go from a template
and start from an existing
document that's somewhere else.
So we'll now move to step three.
Now, at this point, this is
where you're going to link the
letter with the data source.
So what you need to do is need to
browse to the location where you
saved the spreadsheet containing
the names and addresses, downloaded.
So I saved these in my documents
folder in the IT course, and
in the word processing folder.
And you'll see this as an
Excel spreadsheet and it is
sample mail merge addresses.
So I just simply double click on that.
And that then gives me the option.
So it's asking me to select the table
and I'm happy with that click OK.
This then brings up the mail
merge recipients dialog box.
So this tells me what the
contents of the spreadsheet are.
So I know there are four people
within that spreadsheet and the
names and addresses are all there.
If I didn't want to send the letter
to a specific person, I can tick or
untick that box and it will remove them.
It won't include them in the merge.
When I'm happy with that, I click OK.
And it is now time to
move on to the next step.
So if I go to step four, this
is about write your letter.
So if you hadn't already done so at
this point you would write the letter.
But what we need to do now is the
letter is already written, so we
simply need to insert the address
block and the greeting line.
So the address block is
traditionally inserted at the top
left-hand section of the letter.
So I will place the cursor there where
I want the address block to appear.
And if I look along to the right if
I click on address block, I then have
the insert address block dialog box.
In here it will show me what
the addresses will look like.
There are four recipients I know of,
so it will then preview each one.
And I'm happy with that.
So I can then select OK.
So we'll insert the
address block merge field.
I'm also going to add the greeting
line and the greeting line would be
just above the main body of text.
So I'll place the cursor there
and select greeting line.
Again, this will give me a
dialogue box, which shows me a
demonstration of a preview of
what will be seen on the letter.
If I'm happy with that, I click OK
and that inserts the greeting line.
So now what we need to do is
we need to preview the letters.
So I click on step five.
You can see that the address block and the
greeting line have changed and are now the
full names and addresses of the people.
Again, I can preview each of the
letters to see that I'm happy with it.
I can exclude recipients, or I can even
edit the recipient list at this point.
So the final step would
be to complete the merge.
If I selected print, I can then select
all and I could print out the letters.